<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="xdg_shell">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2008-2013 Kristian Høgsberg
    Copyright © 2013      Rafael Antognolli
    Copyright © 2013      Jasper St. Pierre
    Copyright © 2010-2013 Intel Corporation

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice (including the next
    paragraph) shall be included in all copies or substantial portions of the
    Software.

    THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
    IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
    FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT.  IN NO EVENT SHALL
    THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
    LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING
    FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER
    DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="xdg_shell" version="1">
    <description summary="create desktop-style surfaces">
      xdg_shell allows clients to turn a wl_surface into a "real window"
      which can be dragged, resized, stacked, and moved around by the
      user. Everything about this interface is suited towards traditional
      desktop environments.
    </description>

    <enum name="version">
      <description summary="latest protocol version">
	The 'current' member of this enum gives the version of the
	protocol.  Implementations can compare this to the version
	they implement using static_assert to ensure the protocol and
	implementation versions match.
      </description>
      <entry name="current" value="5" summary="Always the latest version"/>
    </enum>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="role" value="0" summary="given wl_surface has another role"/>
      <entry name="defunct_surfaces" value="1" summary="xdg_shell was destroyed before children"/>
      <entry name="not_the_topmost_popup" value="2" summary="the client tried to map or destroy a non-topmost popup"/>
      <entry name="invalid_popup_parent" value="3" summary="the client specified an invalid popup parent surface"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy xdg_shell">
        Destroy this xdg_shell object.

        Destroying a bound xdg_shell object while there are surfaces
        still alive created by this xdg_shell object instance is illegal
        and will result in a protocol error.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="use_unstable_version">
      <description summary="enable use of this unstable version">
	Negotiate the unstable version of the interface.  This
	mechanism is in place to ensure client and server agree on the
	unstable versions of the protocol that they speak or exit
	cleanly if they don't agree.  This request will go away once
	the xdg-shell protocol is stable.
      </description>
      <arg name="version" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <request name="get_xdg_surface">
      <description summary="create a shell surface from a surface">
	This creates an xdg_surface for the given surface and gives it the
	xdg_surface role. A wl_surface can only be given an xdg_surface role
	once. If get_xdg_surface is called with a wl_surface that already has
	an active xdg_surface associated with it, or if it had any other role,
	an error is raised.

	See the documentation of xdg_surface for more details about what an
	xdg_surface is and how it is used.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="xdg_surface"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
    </request>

    <request name="get_xdg_popup">
      <description summary="create a popup for a surface">
	This creates an xdg_popup for the given surface and gives it the
	xdg_popup role. A wl_surface can only be given an xdg_popup role
	once. If get_xdg_popup is called with a wl_surface that already has
	an active xdg_popup associated with it, or if it had any other role,
	an error is raised.

	This request must be used in response to some sort of user action
	like a button press, key press, or touch down event.

	See the documentation of xdg_popup for more details about what an
	xdg_popup is and how it is used.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="xdg_popup"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="parent" type="object" interface="wl_surface"/>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="the wl_seat of the user event"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial of the user event"/>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <event name="ping">
      <description summary="check if the client is alive">
        The ping event asks the client if it's still alive. Pass the
        serial specified in the event back to the compositor by sending
        a "pong" request back with the specified serial.

        Compositors can use this to determine if the client is still
        alive. It's unspecified what will happen if the client doesn't
        respond to the ping request, or in what timeframe. Clients should
        try to respond in a reasonable amount of time.

        A compositor is free to ping in any way it wants, but a client must
        always respond to any xdg_shell object it created.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="pass this to the pong request"/>
    </event>

    <request name="pong">
      <description summary="respond to a ping event">
	A client must respond to a ping event with a pong request or
	the client may be deemed unresponsive.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="serial of the ping event"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="xdg_surface" version="1">
    <description summary="A desktop window">
      An interface that may be implemented by a wl_surface, for
      implementations that provide a desktop-style user interface.

      It provides requests to treat surfaces like windows, allowing to set
      properties like maximized, fullscreen, minimized, and to move and resize
      them, and associate metadata like title and app id.

      The client must call wl_surface.commit on the corresponding wl_surface
      for the xdg_surface state to take effect. Prior to committing the new
      state, it can set up initial configuration, such as maximizing or setting
      a window geometry.

      Even without attaching a buffer the compositor must respond to initial
      committed configuration, for instance sending a configure event with
      expected window geometry if the client maximized its surface during
      initialization.

      For a surface to be mapped by the compositor the client must have
      committed both an xdg_surface state and a buffer.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="Destroy the xdg_surface">
	Unmap and destroy the window. The window will be effectively
	hidden from the user's point of view, and all state like
	maximization, fullscreen, and so on, will be lost.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_parent">
      <description summary="set the parent of this surface">
	Set the "parent" of this surface. This window should be stacked
	above a parent. The parent surface must be mapped as long as this
	surface is mapped.

	Parent windows should be set on dialogs, toolboxes, or other
	"auxiliary" surfaces, so that the parent is raised when the dialog
	is raised.
      </description>
      <arg name="parent" type="object" interface="xdg_surface" allow-null="true"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_title">
      <description summary="set surface title">
	Set a short title for the surface.

	This string may be used to identify the surface in a task bar,
	window list, or other user interface elements provided by the
	compositor.

	The string must be encoded in UTF-8.
      </description>
      <arg name="title" type="string"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_app_id">
      <description summary="set application ID">
	Set an application identifier for the surface.

	The app ID identifies the general class of applications to which
	the surface belongs. The compositor can use this to group multiple
	surfaces together, or to determine how to launch a new application.

	For D-Bus activatable applications, the app ID is used as the D-Bus
	service name.

	The compositor shell will try to group application surfaces together
	by their app ID.  As a best practice, it is suggested to select app
	ID's that match the basename of the application's .desktop file.
	For example, "org.freedesktop.FooViewer" where the .desktop file is
	"org.freedesktop.FooViewer.desktop".

	See the desktop-entry specification [0] for more details on
	application identifiers and how they relate to well-known D-Bus
	names and .desktop files.

	[0] http://standards.freedesktop.org/desktop-entry-spec/
      </description>
      <arg name="app_id" type="string"/>
    </request>

    <request name="show_window_menu">
      <description summary="show the window menu">
        Clients implementing client-side decorations might want to show
        a context menu when right-clicking on the decorations, giving the
        user a menu that they can use to maximize or minimize the window.

        This request asks the compositor to pop up such a window menu at
        the given position, relative to the local surface coordinates of
        the parent surface. There are no guarantees as to what menu items
        the window menu contains.

        This request must be used in response to some sort of user action
        like a button press, key press, or touch down event.
      </description>

      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="the wl_seat of the user event"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial of the user event"/>
      <arg name="x" type="int" summary="the x position to pop up the window menu at"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int" summary="the y position to pop up the window menu at"/>
    </request>

    <request name="move">
      <description summary="start an interactive move">
	Start an interactive, user-driven move of the surface.

	This request must be used in response to some sort of user action
	like a button press, key press, or touch down event. The passed
	serial is used to determine the type of interactive move (touch,
	pointer, etc).

	The server may ignore move requests depending on the state of
	the surface (e.g. fullscreen or maximized), or if the passed serial
	is no longer valid.

	If triggered, the surface will lose the focus of the device
	(wl_pointer, wl_touch, etc) used for the move. It is up to the
	compositor to visually indicate that the move is taking place, such as
	updating a pointer cursor, during the move. There is no guarantee
	that the device focus will return when the move is completed.
      </description>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="the wl_seat of the user event"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial of the user event"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="resize_edge">
      <description summary="edge values for resizing">
	These values are used to indicate which edge of a surface
	is being dragged in a resize operation.
      </description>
      <entry name="none" value="0"/>
      <entry name="top" value="1"/>
      <entry name="bottom" value="2"/>
      <entry name="left" value="4"/>
      <entry name="top_left" value="5"/>
      <entry name="bottom_left" value="6"/>
      <entry name="right" value="8"/>
      <entry name="top_right" value="9"/>
      <entry name="bottom_right" value="10"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="resize">
      <description summary="start an interactive resize">
	Start a user-driven, interactive resize of the surface.

	This request must be used in response to some sort of user action
	like a button press, key press, or touch down event. The passed
	serial is used to determine the type of interactive resize (touch,
	pointer, etc).

	The server may ignore resize requests depending on the state of
	the surface (e.g. fullscreen or maximized).

	If triggered, the client will receive configure events with the
	"resize" state enum value and the expected sizes. See the "resize"
	enum value for more details about what is required. The client
	must also acknowledge configure events using "ack_configure". After
	the resize is completed, the client will receive another "configure"
	event without the resize state.

	If triggered, the surface also will lose the focus of the device
	(wl_pointer, wl_touch, etc) used for the resize. It is up to the
	compositor to visually indicate that the resize is taking place,
	such as updating a pointer cursor, during the resize. There is no
	guarantee that the device focus will return when the resize is
	completed.

	The edges parameter specifies how the surface should be resized,
	and is one of the values of the resize_edge enum. The compositor
	may use this information to update the surface position for
	example when dragging the top left corner. The compositor may also
	use this information to adapt its behavior, e.g. choose an
	appropriate cursor image.
      </description>
      <arg name="seat" type="object" interface="wl_seat" summary="the wl_seat of the user event"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial of the user event"/>
      <arg name="edges" type="uint" summary="which edge or corner is being dragged"/>
    </request>

    <enum name="state">
      <description summary="types of state on the surface">
        The different state values used on the surface. This is designed for
        state values like maximized, fullscreen. It is paired with the
        configure event to ensure that both the client and the compositor
        setting the state can be synchronized.

        States set in this way are double-buffered. They will get applied on
        the next commit.

        Desktop environments may extend this enum by taking up a range of
        values and documenting the range they chose in this description.
        They are not required to document the values for the range that they
        chose. Ideally, any good extensions from a desktop environment should
        make its way into standardization into this enum.

        The current reserved ranges are:

        0x0000 - 0x0FFF: xdg-shell core values, documented below.
        0x1000 - 0x1FFF: GNOME
      </description>
      <entry name="maximized" value="1" summary="the surface is maximized">
        The surface is maximized. The window geometry specified in the configure
        event must be obeyed by the client.
      </entry>
      <entry name="fullscreen" value="2" summary="the surface is fullscreen">
        The surface is fullscreen. The window geometry specified in the configure
        event must be obeyed by the client.
      </entry>
      <entry name="resizing" value="3">
        The surface is being resized. The window geometry specified in the
        configure event is a maximum; the client cannot resize beyond it.
        Clients that have aspect ratio or cell sizing configuration can use
        a smaller size, however.
      </entry>
      <entry name="activated" value="4">
        Client window decorations should be painted as if the window is
        active. Do not assume this means that the window actually has
        keyboard or pointer focus.
      </entry>
    </enum>

    <event name="configure">
      <description summary="suggest a surface change">
	The configure event asks the client to resize its surface or to
	change its state.

	The width and height arguments specify a hint to the window
	about how its surface should be resized in window geometry
	coordinates. See set_window_geometry.

	If the width or height arguments are zero, it means the client
	should decide its own window dimension. This may happen when the
	compositor need to configure the state of the surface but doesn't
	have any information about any previous or expected dimension.

	The states listed in the event specify how the width/height
	arguments should be interpreted, and possibly how it should be
	drawn.

	Clients should arrange their surface for the new size and
	states, and then send a ack_configure request with the serial
	sent in this configure event at some point before committing
	the new surface.

	If the client receives multiple configure events before it
        can respond to one, it is free to discard all but the last
        event it received.
      </description>

      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
      <arg name="states" type="array"/>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint"/>
    </event>

    <request name="ack_configure">
      <description summary="ack a configure event">
        When a configure event is received, if a client commits the
        surface in response to the configure event, then the client
        must make a ack_configure request before the commit request,
        passing along the serial of the configure event.

        For instance, the compositor might use this information to move
        a surface to the top left only when the client has drawn itself
        for the maximized or fullscreen state.

        If the client receives multiple configure events before it
        can respond to one, it only has to ack the last configure event.
      </description>
      <arg name="serial" type="uint" summary="the serial from the configure event"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_window_geometry">
      <description summary="set the new window geometry">
        The window geometry of a window is its "visible bounds" from the
        user's perspective. Client-side decorations often have invisible
        portions like drop-shadows which should be ignored for the
        purposes of aligning, placing and constraining windows.

        The window geometry is double buffered, and will be applied at the
        time wl_surface.commit of the corresponding wl_surface is called.

        Once the window geometry of the surface is set once, it is not
        possible to unset it, and it will remain the same until
        set_window_geometry is called again, even if a new subsurface or
        buffer is attached.

        If never set, the value is the full bounds of the surface,
        including any subsurfaces. This updates dynamically on every
        commit. This unset mode is meant for extremely simple clients.

        If responding to a configure event, the window geometry in here
        must respect the sizing negotiations specified by the states in
        the configure event.

        The arguments are given in the surface local coordinate space of
        the wl_surface associated with this xdg_surface.

        The width and height must be greater than zero.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="int"/>
      <arg name="y" type="int"/>
      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
    </request>

    <request name="set_maximized">
      <description summary="maximize the window">
        Maximize the surface.

        After requesting that the surface should be maximized, the compositor
        will respond by emitting a configure event with the "maximized" state
        and the required window geometry. The client should then update its
        content, drawing it in a maximized state, i.e. without shadow or other
        decoration outside of the window geometry. The client must also
        acknowledge the configure when committing the new content (see
        ack_configure).

        It is up to the compositor to decide how and where to maximize the
        surface, for example which output and what region of the screen should
        be used.

        If the surface was already maximized, the compositor will still emit
        a configure event with the "maximized" state.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="unset_maximized">
      <description summary="unmaximize the window">
        Unmaximize the surface.

        After requesting that the surface should be unmaximized, the compositor
        will respond by emitting a configure event without the "maximized"
        state. If available, the compositor will include the window geometry
        dimensions the window had prior to being maximized in the configure
        request. The client must then update its content, drawing it in a
        regular state, i.e. potentially with shadow, etc. The client must also
        acknowledge the configure when committing the new content (see
        ack_configure).

        It is up to the compositor to position the surface after it was
        unmaximized; usually the position the surface had before maximizing, if
        applicable.

        If the surface was already not maximized, the compositor will still
        emit a configure event without the "maximized" state.
      </description>
    </request>

    <request name="set_fullscreen">
      <description summary="set the window as fullscreen on a monitor">
	Make the surface fullscreen.

        You can specify an output that you would prefer to be fullscreen.
	If this value is NULL, it's up to the compositor to choose which
        display will be used to map this surface.

        If the surface doesn't cover the whole output, the compositor will
        position the surface in the center of the output and compensate with
        black borders filling the rest of the output.
      </description>
      <arg name="output" type="object" interface="wl_output" allow-null="true"/>
    </request>
    <request name="unset_fullscreen" />

    <request name="set_minimized">
      <description summary="set the window as minimized">
	Request that the compositor minimize your surface. There is no
	way to know if the surface is currently minimized, nor is there
	any way to unset minimization on this surface.

	If you are looking to throttle redrawing when minimized, please
	instead use the wl_surface.frame event for this, as this will
	also work with live previews on windows in Alt-Tab, Expose or
	similar compositor features.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="close">
      <description summary="surface wants to be closed">
        The close event is sent by the compositor when the user
        wants the surface to be closed. This should be equivalent to
        the user clicking the close button in client-side decorations,
        if your application has any...

        This is only a request that the user intends to close your
        window. The client may choose to ignore this request, or show
        a dialog to ask the user to save their data...
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>

  <interface name="xdg_popup" version="1">
    <description summary="short-lived, popup surfaces for menus">
      A popup surface is a short-lived, temporary surface that can be
      used to implement menus. It takes an explicit grab on the surface
      that will be dismissed when the user dismisses the popup. This can
      be done by the user clicking outside the surface, using the keyboard,
      or even locking the screen through closing the lid or a timeout.

      When the popup is dismissed, a popup_done event will be sent out,
      and at the same time the surface will be unmapped. The xdg_popup
      object is now inert and cannot be reactivated, so clients should
      destroy it. Explicitly destroying the xdg_popup object will also
      dismiss the popup and unmap the surface.

      Clients will receive events for all their surfaces during this
      grab (which is an "owner-events" grab in X11 parlance). This is
      done so that users can navigate through submenus and other
      "nested" popup windows without having to dismiss the topmost
      popup.

      Clients that want to dismiss the popup when another surface of
      their own is clicked should dismiss the popup using the destroy
      request.

      The parent surface must have either an xdg_surface or xdg_popup
      role.

      Specifying an xdg_popup for the parent means that the popups are
      nested, with this popup now being the topmost popup. Nested
      popups must be destroyed in the reverse order they were created
      in, e.g. the only popup you are allowed to destroy at all times
      is the topmost one.

      If there is an existing popup when creating a new popup, the
      parent must be the current topmost popup.

      A parent surface must be mapped before the new popup is mapped.

      When compositors choose to dismiss a popup, they will likely
      dismiss every nested popup as well. When a compositor dismisses
      popups, it will follow the same dismissing order as required
      from the client.

      The x and y arguments passed when creating the popup object specify
      where the top left of the popup should be placed, relative to the
      local surface coordinates of the parent surface. See
      xdg_shell.get_xdg_popup.

      The client must call wl_surface.commit on the corresponding wl_surface
      for the xdg_popup state to take effect.

      For a surface to be mapped by the compositor the client must have
      committed both the xdg_popup state and a buffer.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="remove xdg_popup interface">
	This destroys the popup. Explicitly destroying the xdg_popup
	object will also dismiss the popup, and unmap the surface.

	If this xdg_popup is not the "topmost" popup, a protocol error
	will be sent.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="popup_done">
      <description summary="popup interaction is done">
	The popup_done event is sent out when a popup is dismissed by the
	compositor. The client should destroy the xdg_popup object at this
	point.
      </description>
    </event>

  </interface>
</protocol>
